In this video, we're going to go over a
few static equilibrium
problems. Now, there are two things that
you need to
know. The net
force must be zero. The sum of all
forces in the x and y
direction must be equal to zero. So, you
have translational
equilibrium. Now, you must also have
rotational equilibrium. So the sum of
all the
torqus must be equal to zero as
well. So when these two conditions are
met then static equilibrium will
occur. Now let's review torqus. Let's
say if you have an object that can
rotate about this pivot
point and if we apply a
force at an
angle and let's say this is
the the length of the bar so to
speak then the torque
is the crossroduct of R and F which is F
* R sin theta where theta is the angle
between R and F. So we're going to use
this formula a lot to calculate the
torque in these
problems. In
addition, we need to talk about the sign
conventions that we're going to use for
our torque calculations. Let's say if we
have two forces
F_sub_1 and
F_sub_2, F_sub_2 will
create a counterclockwise rotation, so
it's going to create a positive
torque. F_sub_1 will create a clockwise
rotation, so it's going to create a
negative
torque. Let's try this problem. A 40 kg
child sits on a seessaw 3 m away from
the pivot point. The mass of the bar is
kg. Where should a 30 kg child sit to
balance the
seesaw? So, let's begin by drawing a
free body
diagram. So, here's the pivot point or
the
fulcrum and here's the first
child. Let's just draw a stick figure.
Now the force the weight force exerted
by the first child let's call
it F1 and this child is 3 m away from
the pivot
point. Now the second
child is X meters away from the pivot
point. That's what we're looking
for. And this child will exert a weight
force that we're going to call
F_sub_2. Now the mass of the bar also
exerts a weight
force and the pivot point exerts an
upward normal
force which supports the other three
downward
forces. So we can calculate the normal
force first or the location where the 30
kg child sit. Doesn't matter what order
we do it. So let's start with the normal
force. So we know that the sum of all
forces in the y direction must be equal
to zero if we are to have static
equilibrium. Now the normal force is an
upward force and the other three forces
are downward forces. So we're going to
put a negative sign in front of it.
Now if we add the three forces with a
negative sign and move it to the left
side of the equation, we can see that
f_sub_1 plus f_sub_2
plus the weight force of the bar is
equal to the normal force exerted by the
pivot
point. So the weight force of the first
child is simply mg. It's 40 kg *
9.8. The weight force of the second
child is 30 kg *
9.8. And the weight force of the bar,
the mass of the bar is 10 kg. So it's
going to be 10 *
9.8. And this should equal the normal
force exerted by the pivot
point. So because each term has a common
number 9.8, we can add 40, 30, and 10,
which is 80. So it's 80 *
9.8 and therefore the normal force
exerted by the pivot point is 784
newtons. Now that we have the normal
force, let's calculate the location
where the 30 kg child should
sit. So now we need to analyze the
torqus created in this situation.
So let's choose the center of rotation
as the pivot
point. So therefore the normal force and
the weight force will not create a
torque because they're located at the
pivot point. Their R value is zero.
Torque is F * R. So if you're directly
on the pivot point, that force will not
create any torque. So there's going to
be two torqus created.
T1, which is a counterclockwise torque,
that's
positive. And T2, that's a clockwise
torque. So that's going to be
negative. So we know that the sum of the
torqus must add up to zero. So that's T1
minus T2. If we add T2 to the other
side, we can see that T2 is equal to T1.
T2 is F_sub_2 * R2. That's X *
F_sub_2. And torque
1 is F_sub_1 * R1.
f_sub_2 is
m_sub_2g. f_sub_1 is
m1g. So if we divide both sides by g, we
can get rid of gravitational
acceleration. So the mass of the second
child is 30 kg * x and the mass of the
first child is 40 kg * r1 which is
3. So let's divide both sides by 30.
So 30 over 40 we can cancel a zero.
That's basically 4 over 3. So it's 4 * 3
/ 3 which we can cancel of 3. So
therefore x is equal to 4.
So to balance the
seessaw, the 30 kg
child needs to sit 4 m away from the
pivot
point. Here's another problem. So, let's
say if this is the wall and here's the
ceiling and if we have a hanging
sign supported by two
ropes and let's say the mass of the
sign is 50
kg. Now let's call
this
force
T1 and the tension in the other
cable
T2. How can we calculate T1 and
T2? What would you do? And let's say
this is the weight force mg.
Well, let's write the equations that we
have.
T1
has an x
component and a y
component. And there's one thing I'm
forgetting, and that's the angle. Let's
say this angle between t1 and the
ceiling is
60°. So that would mean this is 60.
These are alternate interior angles and
they're congruent. So this is 60 as
well. So the sum of the forces in the y
direction must equal
zero. Which means that t1
y minus mg has to equal z. Therefore we
can say that t1 y is equal to mg.
Now, what about the forces in the x
direction? These two must add to
zero. So, we have t1x and
t2. So, t1x is directed towards the
right. So, we're going to put a positive
sign in front of it. And t2 is directed
towards the left, so it's negative. So,
if we add t2 to both sides, we can see
that t2 is equal to t1x.
Now, it turns out that we don't really
need to use torqus to solve for t2 and
t1 in this
equation. But we know that for this to
remain still, the net torque must be
zero. Now, we can calculate t1
y because we know the mass. T1 y is
equal to mg and that's 50
kg time a gravitational acceleration of
9.8. By the way, for these problems,
make sure you always draw a free body
diagram. It helps when you can see all
the
forces. So 50 * 9.8, this is uh
490. So that's uh t1 y. Now if we have
the value of t1 y, we can calculate t.
Now according to SOA
sin theta is equal to the opposite side
T1 Y / the hypotenuse
T. So if you rearrange that equation to
solve for T1 Y, T1 Y is T sin theta or T
sin
60. So to solve for T, it's going to be
490 / sin 60. and make sure your
calculator is in degree mode. So the
tension force is about
568 I mean
565.8
newtons and this is of course
T1. So now that we have the value of T1,
we can calculate T2 by finding
T1X. So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's move this somewhere else.
So t2 which equals t1x and t1x is t1
cosine theta or t1 cosine
60. So this is simply going to be t1
which is 565.8
* cosine of 60°.
And so the tension force in the other
cable is
282.9
newtons. And that's all you got to do
for this
problem. Now let's try another problem
similar to the last
problem. This time we have a hanging
mass that has a mass of 80 kg and we
have two cables. We want to calculate T1
and T2. So what can we do to solve for
the two tension
forces? So we need to draw a free body
diagram. T1 has an x
component which we'll call t1x and it
has a y component t1 y. Now if this
angle is 40 then this angle must also be
40 as well. Now t2 has an x component
and a y component.
T2X and T2Y and this angle is also 50.
And then we have the weight force
mg. So the sum of the forces in the x
direction must be balanced. Therefore,
there's only two forces in the x
direction. And those two forces must
equal each other. They have the same
magnitude, but they're opposite in
direction. So t1x is equal to t2x.
Now the sum of the forces in the y
direction must also add to zero. So t2y
and t1 y has to support the weight force
mg. So we could say that t1 y plus t2y
=
mg. So we have two equations and two
variables t2 and t1.
How can we use these two equations to
solve for these two
variables? So we need to use
substitution to get the answer. So let's
start with this
equation. T1X is T1 cosine
theta and the angle associated with T1
is 40.
t2x is t2 cossine
50. So let's solve for
t2. So t2 is going to be t1 cossine 40 /
cosine 50. And cosine 40 over cosine 50
is about
1.198. So
1.1918 t1 is equal to t2.
Now let's save that equation. So I'm
going to write it
here. Now let's work with the second
equation. T1 y is t1 sin theta. So
that's
t1 sin 40. t2
y is t2 sin
50. And mg is basically 80 *
9.8 which is equal to
784. Now let's replace t2 with
1.1918 t1.
Now let's simplify the expressions that
we now
have. Let's convert everything into
decimal values. Sin 40 is about
64 28 * t1
1.1918
* sin
50 is equal
to
91 3 or 297 which we can round it to a
three uh t1 and that's equal to 784. So
at this point we can combine like terms.
But before we do that let's uh make
space. So
91297 plus
6428. If you add those two this is going
to be
1.5558 t1 and that's equal to 784. So to
solve for T1, let's divide 784 by
1.5558. So T1 is equal to
503.9
newtons. So now that we have the value
of T1, we can calculate
T2 using this equation. So T2 is simply
503.9 time 1.1918.
and you should get about
600.5
newtons. So that's T2 and
T1. Let's try another problem. So let's
say if we have a uniform beam, that's
this object right here. And let's say it
has a
mass of 100 kilogram.
And on top of it, we have a 20 kilogram
box. And let's say that the length of
the
beam is
about 10 m.
And the box is
located 8
mters from the left vertical support
column which is this part right
here. What are the forces exerted by
each support column? So what is the
value of
f_sub_1 and the value of
f_sub_2? What can we do to calculate
these two
forces? Go ahead and try this
problem. So the weight of the beam is
located at the center of
gravity. So that's going to be five
meters from the first vertical column
and from the other one
too. And then we have the weight of the
box which we'll call
mg. So let's write an equation for all
of the forces in the y direction.
So the sum of all forces in the y
direction, it's going to be f_sub_1 plus
f_sub_2. These are upward forces minus
the downward
forces. mg for the beam and mg for the
box. Now we know that the forces in the
y direction must add up to zero if
this situation is to be in static
equilibrium.
mg is going to be the mass of the beam
which is 100 time G which is 9.8 so
that's
980 and the other mg is 20 * 9.8
Okay. So that's uh
196. So let's go ahead and replace these
values. So this is 980 newtons and this
is 196.
So if we add these two and then move it
to the other side, we can see that
f_sub_1 plus
f_sub_2 is equal to 980 + 196 or 1176
newtons. So at this point we only have
one equation but we have two
variables. So to solve those two
variables we need another equation. So
we need to use
torque. So we need to choose an axis of
rotation. We can choose the left support
column or the right support
column because it can cancel either F1
or F_sub_2. It really doesn't matter
which column we choose. Both ways will
give you the same answer. But let's
choose the left support column. So if
this is the axis of
rotation, F_sub_1 will create no
torque. Now
F_sub_2 will create a counterclockwise
torque. So it's going to be
positive. Let's call the torque created
by F_sub_2
T2. And the torque created by the box,
let's call it T1. And because it's
moving in a clockwise direction, that
torque will be negative. And a torque
created by the mass of the beam is also
negative. Let's call it uh we'll call
this one, let's say t1 and t3.
So the sum of all torqus is going to be
t2 which is positive created by f_sub_2
minus t1 which is created by the beam
minus t3 which is the clockwise torque
created by the mass of the
box. So all of these torqus must add up
to zero.
T2 is going to be
F_sub_2 times the moment arm, which is
the distance
between F_sub_2 and the axis of
rotation. So F_sub_2 is about 10 m away
from the axis of
rotation. T1, the torque created by the
mass of the beam, it's about 5 mters
from the axis of rotation. So this is
going to be 980. That's the weight of
the beam times 5. T3, the weight of the
box is 196 and it's 8 m from the axis of
rotation. 980 * 5 is
4900 and 196 * 8 is 1568.
If we add those
two, we should get
6468. So 10 * f_sub_2 - 6468 is equal to
zero. So 10 f_sub_2 is equal to
6468. And if we divide by
10, f_sub_2 is going to be
646.8 newtons.
So now that we have the value for
f_sub_2, we could solve for
f_sub_1. So f_sub_1 + f_sub_2 or 646.8
is equal to
1176. So f_sub_1 is simply 1176 -
646.8. And that's going to be
529.2 newtons.
Now in this problem we have a hanging
mass of 200
kg and the mass of the beam let's say
it's 30
kg and the angle that the tension or the
cable makes with the beam let's say this
is
30° and this is the tension force
E. And here is the hinge which I forgot
to draw. Let's put it there. And so this
is going to be the axis of
rotation. Let's say the distance between
the
hinge and the hanging sign. Let's say
this is
about 2.2 actually just 2 meters.
So with this information, go ahead and
calculate the tension force and also the
components of the forces that the hinge
exerts on the beam. So the hinge is
going to
exert a y component which is we'll call
it
fhy and it's going to exert a force in
the x direction which we'll
call
fhx. So feel free to pause the video and
try this example.
Now we need to realize that the tension
force has a y component which we'll call
ty and it has an x component which we
can call
tx. So the only forces that are acting
in the x direction is f hx and tx. So
these two forces are equal to each
other. So tx is equal to f hx.
So we can't do anything with this
equation right now. So now let's look at
the forces in the y direction. We have
ty
fhy. We also have the weight of the side
which we'll call mg and the weight of
the beam which we'll call uh
capital mg.
So the two upward forces
ty and
fhy they have to support the downward
forces that is the weight of the beam
and the weight of the hanging
sign. So the weight of the beam is going
to be 30 *
9.8 which is
294 and the weight of the sign is 200 *
9.8 which is 1960. If you add 1960 and
294, this is going to be 2254
Newtons. So that's equal to T Y +
FHY. Right now we have two equations and
four different variables. So we need
more
information. So now let's analyze the
torqus in this problem. Ty is going to
create a torque in the counterclockwise
direction. So that torque is going to be
positive and let's call it
T1. MG is going to create a torque in
the clockwise direction. So that torque
is going to be negative. Let's call it
T2. And the weight of the beam will also
create a torque
T3. Now if we choose the hinge as the
axis of rotation, then these forces will
create no torque because the R value
will be
zero. So therefore we can write an
equation for the sum of all torqus. It's
going to be T1 which is
positive minus torque 2 and torque
3. Now the net torque has to add up to
zero. And T1 is basically
TY times the length of the beam which is
2 m. And TY is T sin
theta. And the angle is 30. So it's sin
30 * 2 and then minus
t2 which has a weight force of 200 * 9.8
and that's
1960 times an r
value or moment arm of two and then
minus t3 which has a weight force of 30
* 9.8 8, which is
294 and it's at the center of gravity,
so it's half of 2. So that's 1. So it's
294 *
1. Sin 30 is 12. And 12 * 2 is 1. So
this is simply t. 1960 * 2 is
3920. And if we add 294 and 3920, we're
going to get 4214.
So that's the tension force
T. Now that we have the value of
T, we can calculate everything else that
we
need. So let's find the X component of
the force that the the hinge exerts on
the beam.
So let's calculate f hhx which is equal
to tx and
tx is t cosine theta and t is
4214 and then times cossine
30. So this is equal
to
49.4 newtons.
So that's the x component of the the
force exerted by the hinge. Now to find
the y component, we need to use the
second
equation which is uh this one. So ty is
going to be uh t sin
theta plus
fhy and that's equal to
2254. Now t is
4214 time sin
30 plus the other stuff.
Sin 30 is a half and half of 42 14 is
basically uh
21 07. Half of 42 is 21 half of 14 is
7. So therefore f of hy is
2254 minus
21107 which is 147 units. So that is it
for this problem.
So here we have another hanging sign
problem. The mass of the sign is 15
kg. We have a tension force
T by means of the
cable and it forms an angle of 30° with
the beam.
Now the length of the
beam that's
about 10
m and the mass of the beam is 20 kg.
And this distance is about let's say 4
meters
between where the uh tension force
connects with the pole and the hinge or
the pivot point.
So with this information, go ahead and
find the tension
force and the x and y
components of the force that the hinge
exerts on a beam. So that's uh fx,
fhx, and
uh
fhy. So let's go ahead and solve it. So
let's look at the forces in the x
direction.
The tension force is completely
horizontal. So this is the same as TX.
It has to be equal to
FHx. Those are the only two forces
acting in the x
direction. Now in the y
direction we have an upward
uh force exerted by the hinge fhy and
that supports the weight of the beam and
the weight of the hanging sign. So we
could say that
FHY is equal
to mg that's the weight of the beam
which is basically 20 *
9.8 which is
196 plus mg the weight of the sign which
is uh 15 * 9.8 and that's 147.
So if we add these two numbers, we could
see that
FHY is equal to 343
newtons. So we need to find T and
FHx. Once we find one of them, then
that's it. We're done with this
problem. Now let's consider the torqus
acting on a system. Our axis of rotation
is going to be the pivot point. So, FHY
and FHX will not create a tension or a
torque around the pivot point. Now, the
tension force will create a positive
counterclockwise torque, which we'll
call
T1. The 15 kg sign will create a torque
that's negative, which we'll call T2.
And the 20 kg beam will create a
negative torque called T3.
So the sum of
torqus the sum of all the torqus it's
going to be uh positive t1 minus t2
minus
t3. So now how can we find
t1? It turns out that torque 1 is simply
the tension force time 4. Four is the
moment arm. Now, for those of you who
are unsure about that, we know that if
you have an object that can rotate, if
you apply a
force, then the perpendicular distance
between where you apply the force and
the line of action of the
force. This is called the moment arm,
that perpendicular distance. And the
torque is simply the product of the
force and the moment arm. Now if you
apply it at an
angle, let's say if you apply the force
here, then the torque is simply FR sin
theta. But let's understand why that's
the
case. When you apply a force at that
point, this is the line of action of the
force.
And the perpendicular distance between
the line of action of the force and the
axis of rotation is this distance right
here. And according to SOA sin theta is
equal to the opposite side which is the
moment
arm divided by the hypotenuse of the
triangle which is across the 90° angle.
And so that's
r. So if you solve for the moment arm
you'll see that it's r sin
theta which gives you the same equation.
So the torque is
F times the moment arm which
is the perpendicular distance between
the line of action and the axis of
rotation.
So therefore for our particular
example
T1 the torque created by the tension
force is simply going to be the tension
force and this is the line of action. So
four is the moment arm that's the
distance between the line of action and
the axis of
rotation. So torque one is simply t * 4.
Now, if you prefer to do it the other
way using the equation f_sub_r sin
theta, you're going to get the same
result, but there's more work involved.
So, let's do it the other way. And so,
you could see why it's t *
4. So, this is going to be the tension
force times the distance between the
axis of rotation and where you apply the
tension force, which is the hypotenuse
of that triangle, time sin theta. Let's
call that distance L.
So notice that L is not 10 is less than
10. 10 is the length of the entire beam.
But we're trying to find L, the distance
between where the tension force acts and
the axis of
rotation. So let's focus on this
particular
triangle and let's redraw it.
So we have a 30° angle. This is the
right angle. This is four. And we're
looking for L. So according to
SOA, sin
theta or sine of 30 is equal to the side
opposite to it, which is 4 / the
hypotenuse, which is across the
box. And so that's
L. Now if we rearrange the equation or
if we cross multiply 1 * 4 is 4
* l sin 30.
So solving for
L, it's going to be 4 / sin
30. Now keep in mind this angle is also
equivalent to sin
30. So now let's plug in L into the
equation. So it's going to be T * L
which is 4 / sin
30 time sin 30. So, as you can see,
these angles will cancel and it's simply
going to be T *
4. So, regardless of which method you
choose to
use, that's going to be the tension
force. I mean, the torque created by the
tension force. It's just four times
T. So, now let's move on to T2 and T3.
So T2 is created by the 15 kg mass. So
it's the weight force which is 15 * 9.8
which we already know it to be
147 time L or the length of the beam but
this is the entire beam which is 10 m
and time sin theta. But now what angle
should we
use? Now let's focus on the 30° angle.
So here's the tension force, here's the
beam, and there's a weight
force. So the angle between the weight
force and the length of the beam, which
you can call it R or L, is this angle,
which is
60°. And even if you analyze another
force, this is going to be 30 and this
is going to be 60 as well.
just based on rules of
geometry. So knowing
that that means
that this angle here is 60° and this
angle is also 60 as well.
So let's multiply 147 and 10 by sin
60 and then minus
t3 which is the weight force created by
the 20 kg mass. So 20 * 9.8 is
196 and it's at the center of gravity.
So it's located at the center of the
beam which is half of 10 and that's 5
m and it creates an angle of 60° between
itself and the beam. So that's sin
60. Now what we need to do is make some
space. So let's get rid of most of this
stuff.
So what we now have is 0 is equal to
4t and 147 * 10 is 1470 * sin 60 and
that's uh
-1273 minus 196 * 5 which is 980 * sin
60 and that's going to be 848.7.
7 1273 +
848.7 that's
2221.7. It's negative on the right side
but if you move it to the left side it's
going to be
positive and that's equal to
14. So now let's divide both sides by
four.
So the tension
force is
530.4 newtons. Now keep in mind the
tension force is also equal to the x
component of the force exerted by the
hinge or the pivot point. So fhx is also
530.4
newtons. So that is it for this problem.
So, here's another problem. Uh, this
time we have a ladder leaning against a
wall and the length of the
ladder is 10
m. and the mass of the
ladder, we're going to say it's uh 8
kg. Calculate all the forces that are
acting on the ladder. So you want to
find the force exerted
by the
wall. Let's call it
FW. And the force exerted by the
ground.
FGX and
also FGY.
Now this distance
here is 8
mters. Feel free to pause the video and
work out this
problem. So let's analyze the forces in
the y direction. We have fg y and the
weight force
mg. So therefore we could say that
fgy has to be equal to
mg. So that's 8 *
9.8 which is about
78.4
newtons. Now notice that the forces in
the x direction are fgx and fw.
So the force exerted by the ground in
the horizontal direction
FGX is equal to the force exerted by the
wall on the ladder
FW. Now we need to
use torqus to solve this particular
problem. So we're going to say this is
the axis of rotation. So we can
eliminate FG Y and FGX from the torque
expression.
And so there's going to be two torqus
that we need to be concerned with.
That's the torque created by FW. That's
going to be a positive torque. We'll
call it uh
T1. And the 8 kg mass will create a
negative torque
t2. So the sum of all torqus is simply
t1 minus t2. And that needs to equal
zero.
T1 is the product of the force on
exerted by the wall and the lever arm.
To easily find the lever
arm, extend the line of action of
FW and draw a parallel line that passes
through the pivot point or the axis of
rotation. The distance between these two
lines is the moment arm, which is eight.
So that's a simple way to find the
moment arm. So it's going to be FW *
8. Now uh
T2 if you notice
it's created by the 8
kg it's created by the weight force of
the 8 kg object. And if we draw a
parallel line that passes through the
axis of rotation the distance between
these two points is the moment arm for
the 8 kg mass.
So this is going to be mg which is 8 *
9.8 that's
78.4 time whatever this distance
is. Now let's uh go back into geometry
or
trigonometry. You need to know special
triangles such as the 345 triangle.
According to the pagan theorem a^2 + b^2
=
c^2 3^2 + 42 =
5^2 32 is 9 42 is 16 9 and 16 is 25
which is
5^2 Now you can also use a similar ratio
instead of the 3 4 5 triangle you can
use the 6 8 10 triangle notice that the
hypotenuse is 10 this side is eight so
the missing side must be
six. So this distance here is 6 m. Which
means the distance that we want between
the two lines, the two yellow lines must
be 3 m. It's half of
six. So torque 2 is going to be the
weight force of the ladder, which is
78.4 times a moment arm of three. So FW
is going to be 78.4 4 * 3 which is
235.2. If you move it to the left side,
it's positive
235.2 / 8. So FW is equal to
29.4
newtons. Now for those of you who like
to get the same answer but using the
other
method, here's what you can do.
So let's get rid of this for now. So
let's say if you simply want to use the
distance of the beam. If you're going to
do it that way, you need to find the
angle between the force and the length
of the
beam. So let's say the length of the
beam is L.
T1 the torque created by FW is going to
be F * L time s of theta where theta is
the angle between the length of the beam
and FW. So that's theta. This is theta
according to um the alternate interior
angle
theorem. So there must be this other
angle. I believe that's called fi if I
remember correctly.
So if you extend the the weight force of
the 8 kilogram
mass this angle is also
phi. So for t2 it's going to be the
weight force mg which is 78.4
4 times the length of the beam times the
angle between the weight force which is
right
here and the beam which is
five. So that's going to be
sign of that
angle. Now let's draw a
triangle. So here's theta. Here's the
other
angle. The hypotenuse is 10. This side
is eight and we know this side is
six. So it's
FW time L where L is
10 time sin theta. Now based on this
triangle sin theta is equal to the
opposite side / the hypotenuse which is
8 / 10. So as you can see uh 10 cancels
and it's just going to be FW * 8 which
we had before minus
78.4. Now this is really supposed to be
L over2 because the 8 kg weight force is
at half of the
beam. It's not at this point where the
length is 10. It's at the middle. So
it's really L over two. So 10 over two
which is five. And sign of the other
angle is going to be opposite which is 6
/ the hypotenuse which is 10. So this is
6 /
10. 5 * 6 is 30 and 30 / 10 is 3. So we
get the same equation FW * 8 - 78.4 4 *
3 and as we know 78.4 * 3 / 8 will give
us the same force of 29.4
newtons. So you want to learn how to do
it the easy way and that is finding the
moment arm that is perpendicular to the
line of action and it's the distance
between
the axis of rotation and the line of
action.
So now that we have
FGX,
FW and
FGY, let's calculate the force that the
ground exerts on the ladder. That is the
resultant force
FG. So FGX is
horizontal. FGY is vertical.
So fg the resultant vector is the
hypotenuse of this triangle. And let's
also calculate the angle that it makes
with the
ground. So according to the pagorean
theorem we know that c^2 is a square b
which means the hypotenuse c is the
roo of a + b. So the hypotenuse f
of g must be the square root of f of
gx^2 plus fg
y^2. So that's going to be the
square of
29.4 2 + 78.4
2. So the resulting force vector is 83.7
newtons. So now that we have that
value we can calculate the angle.
So according to SOA TOA to OA tangent
theta is equal to the opposite side /
the
hypotenuse. So theta is the inverse
tangent of FGY /
FGX. So that's the inverse
tangent. fgy is
78.4. FGX is 29.4.
And so the angle theta is
69.4°. So this is going to be the last
problem for
today. This time we're going to have a
person standing on the ladder.
Now the mass of the
ladder is going to
be let's say uh 10
kilogram. Maybe I should put that on
top.
And the mass of the
person is going to be
kilograms. Now the length of the
ladder, we're going to
say it's 15
m. And we're going to say this
distance is 9 m.
Now, let's say
that the ladder and the wall, there's no
friction between the ladder and the
wall. But at this position where the
person is
located, the ladder begins to slide at
its base. And our goal is to find the
coefficient of static friction in this
problem. When the ladder begins to
slide,
Now, we also
know the length of the base, how far the
base of the ladder is from the wall. And
let's say this distance is 12 m.
And let's say that the
person is
located 8
m from the foot of the
ladder. Now with this information you
can calculate the coefficient of static
friction between the ladder and the
floor or the
ground. So let's begin. Let's label the
forces that we have. So we have the
force exerted by the wall on the ladder
and since this force is perpendicular to
the wall it's by definition a normal
force. Now we also have the force of the
ground
FGY and
also FGX.
Now let's say if we have a box on a
surface, if we apply a force, we know
that static friction will resist the
applied force to keep the box
steady. And there's also the normal
force exerted by the ground on the box.
So notice that the normal force exerted
by the ground is the same as
FGY and the static frictional force is
the same as
FGX. So in this problem you want to
understand that FGY is the normal
force exerted by the ground on the
ladder and FGX is a static frictional
force.
Now we know that static friction is
equal to mu s * normal force. So the
coefficient of static
friction is static friction divided by
the normal force and static friction is
fgx and a normal
force is
fgy. So if we could find fgx and fgy we
could find the coefficient of static
friction. We simply need to divide the
two. So let's begin with the forces in
the x direction. So we know that fgx has
to equal fw because those are the only
forces in the x direction.
And fgy has to support the weight of the
ladder and the weight of the
person. So
fgy is going to
equal
mg the weight of the ladder and mg the
weight of the
person. Now the weight of the ladder is
simply 10 * 9.8 which is 98 newtons. And
the weight of the person is 70 * 9.8
which is 686
newtons. So therefore
fgy which is 98 + 686 that's 784
newtons. So let's conserve
space. Let's get rid of this stuff and
let's move this here.
Now let's consider the
torqus in this problem. So the sum of
all the
torqus is equal to so we have t1 created
by the force of the wall and that's in
the counterclockwise
direction. So that's going to be
positive. T2 created by the weight of
the person that's negative.
and T3 created by the weight of the beam
or the the ladder and that's
negative. So we're going to find the
torqus using the easy method that is
finding the moment arm that is uh
perpendicular to the line of action. So
let's start with t1. The sum of all the
torqus is going to be zero.
So to find the moment arm the easy way,
draw the line of action of the force
that creates torque one, which is FW,
and draw a line that's parallel to that
line, but passes through the pivot
point. The distance between those two
lines is the moment arm. So the moment
arm for FW is nine.
So T1 is going to be FW
* 9. Now let's work with
T2. So torque 2 is created by the weight
of the
person. And so this is the line of
action for the weight force. Let's draw
a parallel line that passes through the
pivot point. And the distance between
these two lines is 8 m. So that's the
moment
arm. So t2 is going to be the weight
force of the 70 kg mass which is uh 70 *
9.8 and that's
686 times the moment arm of 8. Now T3
the weight force for T3 is the 10 kg
mass time 9.8 which is
98. And to find the moment arm, draw a
line
parallel that is the line of action
which is parallel to the weight
force of the
ladder. And let's draw a line parallel
that passes through the pivot
point. And so the distance between these
two lines is the moment arm.
So if this distance is 12 and we know
that the weight of the ladder is right
in the middle at the center of gravity,
this must be six. Half of
12. So it's going to be 98 *
6. 686
*
6 I mean 686 * 8 that's uh 54.88
88 and 98 *
6 is
588. So if we add 5488 +
588 and move it to the other side, it's
going to be
676 is equal to 9 * FW. So if we divide
both sides by
9, the force exerted by the wall is
675.1
Newtons. Now remember FW is the same as
FGX. So fgx is equal to
675.1 newtons. Now that we have fgx and
fgy, we can calculate the coefficient of
static
friction. And so that's uh fgx which is
675.1 / fgy which is 784.
So this is equal
to861. So this is the coefficient of
static friction. So that is it for this
video. Thanks for watching and have a
great day.